UCLA Students. Student Activism materials. 1927-2014. UARC.0259
UCLA Library Special Collections
UCLA Students. Student Activism materials.
1927-1986
UCLA Library Special Collections
UCLA University Archives
UARC.0259
2.8 linear feet (7 boxes)
0.8 linear feet (2 unprocessed document boxes)
1 born-digital carriers (1 hard drive)
4.55 Gigabytes (2 files, 0 folders) Transferred from 1 hard drive.
0.4 linear feet (1 unprocessed document box)
Record Series 259 contains materials related to student activism at UCLA throughout the 20th and early 21st centuries. Themes include communism, pacifism, World War II, the Vietnam War, civil rights, and freedom of expression.
Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9935203453606533
Historical note
Since the university's early years, students at UCLA have been moved by situations at home and abroad to raise their voices in protest.
In the late 1920s and 1939s, student activism was fueled by the social and economic conditions of the Depression era, reaction to the rise of fascism in Europe, threat of war, and political repression at home, particularly against Leftist groups. Students held a strike for peace, and demanded the freedom to express their beliefs without enduring academic repercussion.
Academic freedom remained a much-discussed issue in the 1940s, as students reacted to World War II and its aftermath. Issues such as discrimination and labor rights took greater prominence as veterans returned to campus in the late 1940s.
Controversy over the Loyalty Oath at the University of California, brought on by national anti-communism sentiments, ushered in the 1950s. Discrimination, labor rights, and freedom of expression remained active topics.
The early 1960s saw students engaged in the Civil Rights Movement, protesting against segregation and for racial equality. Student activism during this period also critiqued the university system and the nature of modern American higher education, as evidenced in the Free Speech Movement which made its appearance at UCLA in December 1964.
Peace and antiwar movements, especially concerning American involvement in Vietnam, intensified during the late 1960s and early 1970s, resulting in a strike of students, faculty, and staff. Students were roused to action in support of Black and minority rights, with outrage and vehement protests by the UCLA campus community following the Angela Davis controversy. The assassination of Martin Luther King Jr., the women's liberation movement, and police violence on college and university campuses inspired student action.
Student activism in the mid and late 1970s critiqued the University of California's association with international programs as students turned their attention to events in South East Asia and South America. At home, the labor rights of farmworkers, funding for higher education, and environmentalism took focus.
During the 1980s students protested in opposition to apartheid in South Africa, and the University of California's financial ties to supporters of apartheid. Protests were held in support of political movements in Central and South America. Concerns over nuclear war and nuclear energy also engaged students.
The cessation of affirmative action at UCLA prompted student activism in the 1990s, as did educational budget cuts enacted by the University of California Regents, and experimentation on animals. The 1990s also saw the establishment of a Chicana/o Studies Department at UCLA.
A resurgence of anti-war movements began in the 2000s, while concerns over the cost of higher education remained an issue.
Students at UCLA continue to engage in activism over local, national, and international concerns as they arise.
Scope and Content
Record Series 259 contains materials related to student activism at UCLA from 1927-2014. Files contain materials generated by, or intended for, UCLA students.
Subjects include but are not limited to free speech, communism, pacifism, socialism, freedom of the press, resale of books/student book store, parking on campus, WWII, racial discrimination, Jim Crow, affordable housing, job security, the Loyalty Oath controversy, the Korean War, McCarthyism, the Rosenberg trial, the visit of the Shah of Iran to UCLA, the Civil Rights Movement, desegregation, Selma, the Vietnam War, draft resistance, labor rights, farm worker rights, women's liberation, abortion, Chicano/a rights, Martin Luther King Jr., the Black Panther Party, elections, and religion.
Materials include circulars, leaflets, fliers, pamphlets, newsletters, campaign materials, protest literature, clippings, publications, bulletins, letters, press releases, ephemera, correspondence; and meeting, demonstration, conference, and event documentation.
This is an active record series; additional University records are expected to be added.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically. Folder titles refer to dominant themes of materials within a given period of time, but are not comprehensive lists of all subjects mentioned.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Student Activism Collection (41 items)
Related Material
For more on student activism, see also: Public Information Office. Administrative Files of Chandler Harris (University Archives Record Series 543).
For images of students engaging in activism, see: UCLA University Archives. Photographs (Reference Collection) (University Archives Record Series 100).
Ephemera.; Student newspapers and periodicals
- World peace., 1927-1928. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Campus issues (parking, discipline, credits); international youth; freedom of expression/pacifism; social progress., 1931-1933. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Student expulsion/freedom of expression; communism; labor rights; war/military presence on campus; student expenses; anti-fascism; KKK., 1934. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings (communism, pacifism)., 1934. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Anti-war; communism; freedom of expression; academic freedom; higher education funding; ROTC; student bookstore., 1935. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Clippings (communism, pacifism, strike, hazing)., 1935. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Student strike for peace; academic freedom; communism; labor rights; KKK., 1936. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Student strike for peace; socialism; anti-fascism., 1937. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Student strike for peace; campus issues; "Ham and Eggs" movement. Includes songbook., 1938. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Anti-war; socialism; communism; Ludlow Amendment; co-op bookstore., 1939. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Communism; socialism; WWII; pacifism; Jim Crow., 1940. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- WWII; anti-war; conscription/draft; ROTC; censorship; Jim Crow; co-op bookstore., 1941. (Box 2, Folders 2-3)
- War effort; draft; elections; unions; communism., 1942. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- WWII, international youth., 1943. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- WWII reactions; elections., 1944. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Student life; radicalism., 1945. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Communism; employment; labor rights; Jim Crow; campus housing., 1946. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Communism; labor rights; campus housing/discrimination; Jim Crow., 1947. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Labor rights; anti-fascism; communism; peace/draft; discrimination/Jim Crow (barbers in Westwood); elections; free press., 1948. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Communism; socialism; anti-fascism; veterans; police violence; elections., 1948. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Socialism; communism; loyalty oath/academic freedom; Jim Crow; ROTC; co-op bookstore., 1949. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- WWII; military training at UCLA; student strike for peace; youth roles., 1940's. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Socialism; communism; labor party; loyalty oath; housing discrimination; Jim Crow; peace; ROTC., 1950. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Loyalty oath; Korean War; communism; socialism., 1951. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Rosenbergs; communism; socialism., 1952. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Rosenbergs; housing., 1953. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- ROTC; Mexican-American education; socialism., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Free press/independent student newspaper; NAACP., 1955. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- NAACP; labor rights/strikes; academic freedom., 1956. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Free press; socialism., 1957. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Discrimination/civil rights; communism; socialism; academic freedom/loyalty oath., 1950's. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Segregation; religion; ROTC., 1960-1961. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Communism; socialism; segregation/discrimination; labor rights; academic freedom; House Un-American Activities Committee., 1962. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Socialism; communism; civil rights; labor rights; John F. Kennedy assassination; abortion; Iran; campus issues., 1963. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Free speech; fair housing; discrimination; segregation; elections; Iran/Shah's visit to UCLA., 1964. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Iran; Vietnam; abortion; labor rights; free speech; sexuality; Selma/desegregation; parking., 1965. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Vietnam; sexuality; labor rights., 1966. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Vietnam; labor rights; tuition; abortion; racism., 1967. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Martin Luther King Jr. assassination; women's liberation; free speech; religion; elections; racism; Vietnam/draft resistance., 1968. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Racism; Angela Davis; environmentalism; academic freedom; Chicano Studies; ROTC; Vietnam; UC (University of California) strike., 1969. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Vietnam; police oppression/ROTC; police occupation at UC Berkeley; labor rights; minority rights; Angela Davis; Eldridge Cleaver; women's liberation; environmentalism; UC Regents/campus issues., 1969. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Religions; American Nazi Party; racism; academic freedom; student strike; Vietnam/draft; women's liberation., 1960's. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Political campaigns; women's liberation; abortion; childcare; labor rights; minority rights; racism., 1970. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Newspapers., 1970. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Student and faculty strike; crisis curriculum; tuition; police presence on campus., 1970. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Vietnam., 1970. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Vietnam; elections; labor rights; social revolution; religion; women's liberation; Iran; environmentalism; co-ops; campus issues; parking., 1971. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Vietnam; campus issues; labor rights; elections; religion; Iran., 1972. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Convenio/University of Chile program; racism; elections; socialism; psychosurgery/Center for the Study and Reduction of Violence; religion; Iran, Native American rights., 1973. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Psychosurgery/Center for the Study and Reduction of Violence; racism; elections; Iran; Chile, religion., 1974-1975. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Socialism; labor rights; racism; Vietnam., 1976. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Labor rights/farmworkers; higher education funding; Iran; Palestine; Vietnam; racism., 1977. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Elections; environmentalism; nuclear power; religion; communism; Iran; Chile; South Africa/Apartheid., 1978. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Nuclear power; labor rights/lettuce strike; religion; ROTC; communism; police corruption; KKK; Iran; Puerto Rican independence., 1979. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Vietnam/draft; elections., 1970's. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Draft; ROTC; anti-war; political campaigns; nuclear power; racism; communism; Iran's Shah., 1980. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- UCLA's nuclear reactor; draft/anti-war; international issues; women's rights; religion; unemployment/student expenses; affirmative action., 1981. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- International issues (El Salvador, Iran, Poland, Israel, Central America); disarmament; Reaganomics; communism., 1982. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Racism; higher education funding; El Salvador/Central America; religion; women's rights; disarmament., 1983. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- International issues (El Salvador, Central America, Russia, Middle East, South Africa)., 1984. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Divestment; anti-apartheid; Central America; Pakistan., 1985. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- South Africa; Central America/CIA; police state., 1986. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Animal rights; political campaigns; campus issues., 1988. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Animal rights/experimentation; campus issues; women's rights; labor rights., 1989. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- UC student fee rates; El Salvador., 1992. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Establishment of Chicano/a Studies Center; dissolution/restructuring of departments; Justice for Janitors; student elections., 1993. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Immigration/Proposition 187; student fees/higher education funding; Americorp; ROTC/LGBT rights; elections., 1994. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Affirmative action., 1995. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Affirmative action/Proposition 209; student fees; elections; gender issues; police brutality., 1996. (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Graduate student strike/labor rights; Propositions 226/227; animal research., 1998. (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Anti-impeachment; animal liberation., 1999. (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Affirmative action; dissolution/restructuring of departments., 1990's. (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Elections., 2000. (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Elections; anti-war., 2001. (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Anti-war., 2003. (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Elections., 2004. (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Student fees; labor rights; Minutemen., 2007-2009. (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Student fees; use of police force., 2010. (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Graduate student labor., 2014. (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Socialism; Vietnam/draft; student strikes; academic freedom; freedom of speech; police use of force; ROTC; Jim Crow/segregation; labor rights; religion; elections; LGBT rights; tuition., Undated. (Box 7, Folder 25)